Murder Victims Families for Reconciliation; Records apap313
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation Records1977-2007
1994-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation
apap313
13.5 cubic ft.
The Murder Victims’ Families for Reconciliation Records document the organization’s efforts to abolish the death penalty in all cases. The organization includes family members of both homicide victims and those executed as well as their respective supporter. Included in the collection are handwritten notes, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, brochures, booklets, programs, information packets, photographs, flyers, proofs, drafts, manuscripts, correspondence, memos, transcripts, mailing lists, schedules, meeting agenda, meeting minutes, meeting summaries, by-laws, manuals, checklists, worksheets, evaluation forms, resumes, applications, forms, financial summaries, budgets, contracts, court proceedings, legislative bills, amici curiae, memorabilia, audio/video materials.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of select folders that are marked on the inventory. Researchers with inquiries about this material should contact the head of special collections.
Acquisition Information
The Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation Records were donated by Beth Wood, former Executive Director of the organization, in July 2009.
Administrative History
In 1976, the United States Supreme Court voted to allow the reinstatement of the death penalty. Members of Amnesty International’s Death Penalty Committee immediately reacted and began meeting to create an abolition strategy. One member of this committee, Marie Deans, felt like the committee was almost entirely focused on people on death row, little mention was made about the feelings of murder victims or their surviving families. Marie personally knew what it was like to be a family member of a murder victim, her mother-in-law, Penny Deans, had been killed in 1972 by an escaped convict. The Deans family opposed the death penalty and voiced their opinion during the murder trial which caused them to be harshly criticized by their community. Based on her own experience, Marie began to talk about the experience of the victim at Amnesty International meetings. A few fellow members of Amnesty International agreed that victims’ voices needed to be heard and decided to launch a national group that would allow murder victims to share their opposition to the death penalty. After tracking down other family members of murder victims, Murder Victims’ Families Against the Death Penalty was formed. The small, loose-knit group made it their mission to speak about the needs of victims and opposition to the death penalty.
By the 1980s, executions had dramatically increased and organization members were kept busy by responding to scheduled executions and proposed legislative bills. Members knew that they had to do more than just react, they needed to be able to plan and carry out their own events in opposition to the death penalty. Board members met in Albany, NY in 1988 to discuss how the organization could be more proactive. To be able to react in the way they wanted, the organization needed to be more formally organized. In the early 1990s, the organization became incorporated and received tax exempt status. At the same time, the organization decided to change its name. Now the group would be known as Murder Victims’ Families for Reconciliation. This name change was meant to show the full range of the organizations mission, they not only fought against the death penalty but were for alternatives and for programs that addressed the needs of victims. With this name change in effect, the organization elected an organizing board of directors, began putting out a newsletter, The Voice, and created a website.
With a formal structure in place, Murder Victims’ Families for Reconciliation, also known as MVFR, began to organize national events. After two years of planning, the first event was held in 1993. Known as the Journey of Hope, the event was a two week long educational tour in Indiana that made additional stops in Illinois, Kentucky, and Ohio. While only 120 people participated in the event, the effect was powerful and requests came in for additional events. Over the next four years, Journey of Hope hosted 650 events in several states and had 60,000 people participate. By 1997, Journey of Hope became so large that it became its own organization. While the two groups separated, many MVFR members continued to participate in Journey of Hope tours. Journey of Hope events are not the only time that MVFR members speak vocally about their beliefs. MVFR members also participate in state action events where protests against the death penalty are held, provide testimony for court and legislative hearings, meet with victims organizations to discuss victim assistance programs, participate in and hold conferences, and host benefit concerts. Along with this work, MVFR members also organized a prisoner education program in Virginia which focused on Peace Studies and alternatives to violence and created a book and photo text exhibit both named “Not In Our Name”. The book and exhibit combined photos of victims’ families with summaries of their stories and small statements about why they opposed the death penalty.
Membership in MVFR is not just restricted to the family members of victims of violent crimes. Families of the executed are also considered full members of MVFR. Since executions are another form of killing, MVFR feels that the executed and their families are victims also and deserve to have their voices heard. Those who oppose the death penalty but are not related to murder victims can also join MVFR as associate members. Associate members do not have voting rights within the organization and only one associate member may serve on MVFRs board at a time. By allowing associate membership, MVFR was able to broaden its reach and allow other groups to affiliate with it.
Scope and Contents
The Murder Victims’ Families for Reconciliation Records document the organization’s fight to abolish the death penalty on the United States. The collection contains materials ranging from 1977 to 2007 with the bulk of the material being from 1994 to 2003. The main focus of the collection is on events that the organization hosted or took part in and correspondence. Along with these materials, there are also reference materials and administrative files. Please note that there are very few materials dealing with the organizations formation or its day to day activities. The collection includes correspondence, memos, newspaper clippings, newsletters, press releases, fliers, memorabilia, brochures, pamphlets, booklets, manuals, manuscripts, transcripts, reports, drafts, proofs, notes, schedules, meeting agendas, meeting minutes, meeting summaries, annual reports, ballots, evaluation forms, applications, budgets, financial reports, by-laws, contracts, forms, resumes, photographs, court proceedings, legislative bills, amici curiae, mailing lists, checklists, worksheets, floppy disks, zip disks, cassettes, vhs tapes, dvds, and cds.
Monographs that were included with this collection were transferred to the book division of Special Collections. The items that were transferred include “What To Do When the Police Leave: A Guide to the First Days of Traumatic Loss”, “Murdering Myths: The Story Behind the Death Penalty”, “A Call For Justice: An Assessment of Access to Counsel and Quality of Representation in Delinquency Proceedings”, “Human Sacrifice”, “Mockery of Justice: the true story of the Sheppard murder case”, “Be not afraid: overcoming the fear of death”, “This songs for you”, “Last Meal”, “The way of the prisoner: breaking the chains of self through centering prayer and practice”, “Peacemaking circles: from Crime to community”, “Building open societies: Soros Foundations Network 2002 Report”, “Peace by piece: a violence prevention guide for communities”, “Understanding capital punishment: a guide through the death penalty debate”, “Prisons Almanac”; “Innocence and the crisis in the American death penalty”, “Doing Life: Reflections of Men and Women Serving Life Sentences”, “Mandatory justice: eighteen reforms to the death penalty”, and “Responsibility, rehabilitation and restoration: a Catholic perspective on crime and criminal justice”. The catalog records for these monographs are included in Minerva, the University Library Catalog.
The collection includes 5 series which are all arranged alphabetically. When present, the organization’s own arrangement and Foldertitles were preserved but the majority of the arrangement and Foldertitles reflect the archivist’s own decisions. Decisions about Foldernames were based on the subject of the materials as well as who collected or created the materials that were grouped together.
For related materials, please see the Bill Babbitt Paper (APAP-204), Abraham Bonowitz Papers (APAP-186), Journey of Hope. Bill Pelke Records (APAP-205), National Coalition Against the Death Penalty Records (APAP-110), New Yorkers for Alternatives to the Death Penalty Records (APAP-326), and Virginians for Alternatives to Death Penalty Papers (APAP-304). Further information and records related to the death penalty in the United States can be found in the National Death Penalty Archive which is also housed in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives at SUNY Albany.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Death Penalty; Capital punishment--Moral and ethical aspects.; Capital punishment--Political aspects.; Murder victims' families; Victims of crimes--Civil rights--United States.; Administrative Report; Annual reports; Correspondence; Newsletters; Notes; Photographs; Video recordings; Pamphlets; Booklets; Brochures; Clippings (information artifacts); Fliers (printed matter); Transcripts; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts (document genre); Schedules (time plans); Forms (documents); Contracts; Resumes (personnel records); Floppy Disks; VHS (TM); Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation; Journey of Hope; Deans, Marie, 1941-2011; Cushing, Renny
- Administrative Files, 1977-2005, Undated; 1; 1.9 cubic ft.
  Arrangement:
  Arranged Alphabetically.
  Contents:
  Series 1 contains documents relating to the internal procedures and finances of Murder Victims' Families for reconciliation. While there are a few documents that provide evidence of how the organization was set up, the majority of documents focus on hiring, day to day finances, and committee meetings. There are also materials related to strategic planning and the creation of by-laws and organizational procedure. Although the series contains materials from 1977 to 2005, the bulk of the material is from 1996 to 2004. Contained in this series are meeting agendas, meeting minutes, meeting summaries, correspondence, annual reports, ballots, evaluation forms, applications, newsletters, fliers, budgets, financial reports, manuals, by-laws, pamphlets, drafts, notes, reports, contracts, forms, resumes, proofs, floppy disks, and cassettes.
  - Ad Hoc Quarterly Metting Agenda, 2003; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 2001; 2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Ballots - Bus Tour and Cameras in Courts, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Ballots - Journey of Hope Donations plus - Supporting Materials, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Manual, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Board Election, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Board Functions and Evaluations, 1977; 1983; 1986; 1992-1993; 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Board Functions and Evaluations, 1997-1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Board Functions and Evaluations, 1998 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Board Meeting - 4H Center, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Board Meeting - Agenda, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Board Meeting - Chicago, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1998; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Board Meeting Summary, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Board Member Application, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Board Reimbursement, 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Board Resignation Letters, 1995-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Board Retreat, 1995; 1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Budget and Meeting, 1997-1998; 1999; 2000 (Floppy-disk 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Budget and Financials
    Cushing, Renny - Reimbursement
    Haymarket Draft
    Healing the Wounds of Murder
    Income/Expenses
    Investment Reserves
    Letter to Ricardo
    Prejean - Intro and Letter
    Sidebar for Front Page Story
    Victims' Piece
  - Budget and Meeting, 2001; Undated (Floppy-disk 2)
    Board Meeting - September
    Budget Files
    Executive Director Report
    Newsletter Article - Colorado
    Notes
    Talking Points - Victims' Summit
  - Budget and Meeting, 2001; Undated (Floppy-disk 3)
    Board Memo
    Maria's References
    Minutes
    Questions for Account
    Quick Books Backup
  - Budget and Meeting, 2000-2001; 2001 August 29; 2002 (Floppy-disk 4)
    Budget and Actuals
    Grant - Rubin - Renewal Cover Letter
    PWF - Plan
    PWF - Report
    Quick Books
    Quicken Files
    Working Assets - Cover and Report
  - Business Card Proofs, 1977; 2007; Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
  - Budget and Finances- Propsals and Reports, 1999; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Business Card Proofs, 1999; 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - By-Laws, 1994-1997; 1999; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Chapter Stuff, 2000 May 15; Undated (Floppy-disk 5)
    Individual Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation Chapters - Description
    Individual Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation Chapters - Guideline
    Individual Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation Chapters - Memo (May 15th)
  - Chicago Meeting, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - Citizen Bank Accound Reports, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - Cushing, Renny - Expense File, 1999 (Floppy-disk 6)
  - Cushing, Renny - Reimbursement Forms (2001), 2000; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Cusing, Renny - Reimbursement Forms (2001), 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Cushing, Renny - Reimbursement Forms, 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Decision Making Policy, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Director and Officer Liability Policy, 1998-1999; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Director's Reports, 1994; 1996-1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Drafts of Administrative Forms, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Election Reports and Recommendations, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Employee Evaluation [Restricted], 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Eudora Mail Folder(email), 2000 August 16; Undated (Zip-disk 1)
  - Eudora Mail Folder(email), Undated (Zip-disk 2)
  - Executive Director Candidates, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Executive Director Evaluation Form, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Executive Director Reports, 2003; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
  - Financial Review, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
  - Financial Statements, 2000-2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
  - Financial Summaries, 1999; 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
  - Financial Transaction Reports, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
  - Fundraising Committee, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
  - Fundraising Letters, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 41)
  - Grants, 1994; 2005; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 42)
  - Grant - Rubin and Ottinger, Undated (Floppy-disk 7)
    Grant - Ottinger
    Grant - Rubin
  - Grant and Volunteer files, Undated (Floppy-disk 8)
    Grant - King
    Jesuit Volunteer Files
  - Grant, Volunteer, and Meetings, 1999; Undated (Floppy-disk 9)
    Grant - OSI
    Heetan Letter
    History - Notes
    Histom, Tom
    Job Description - Volunteers
    Organizing Points
    Point Plan - Grant Funding
    Ronnie F-B
    Self-Evaluation
    South Africa Tourism File
    Survey
    Tasks for Interns
    Working Paper
  - Income Tax, 2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 43)
  - Injury Notice, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 44)
  - Investment Reserves, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 45)
  - Internship Opportunities, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 46)
  - Itemized Financial Reports, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 47)
  - Jesuit Volunteer Corps Interns [Restricted], 2002-2004; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 48)
  - Jesuit Volunteer Corps Volunteer Program, 1999-2000; 2002-2003; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 49)
  - Job Descriptions, 1995; 1997-1999; 2004; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 50)
  - Liability Insurance, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 51)
  - List of Board and Committee Members, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 52)
  - LLL Database, Undated (Floppy-disk 10)
  - Liz Backup, 2001-2002; 1999 March 8; Undated (Zip-disk 3)
  - Liz Biz DB Backup (June 21st), Undated (Zip-disk 4)
  - Massachusetts Foreign Corporation Annual, 2001; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 53)
  - Massachusetts Public Charities Registration, 1992; 1995; 1999-2000; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 54)
  - Massachusetts Unemployment Insurance, 2005; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 55)
  - Member Questionnaire, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 56)
  - Membership Committee, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 57)
  - Merrill Lynch Account Reports and Changes [Restricted], 2002-2003; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 58)
  - Mission Statement, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 59)
  - Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation Budget for Unified Abolition Strategy, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 60)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 61)
  - Notes on Paperwork needed for Audit, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 62)
  - Office Space Memo, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 63)
  - Operating Budget, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 64)
  - Organization Timeline, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 65)
  - Organizational Budget for the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 66)
  - Organizational Plan, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 67)
  - Organizer Position Application, 2000; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 68)
  - Personnel Policy, 2003; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 69)
  - Phone Logs July-March, 1999-2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 70)
  - Phone Logs March-July, 2000 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Phone Logs November-May, 2000-2001 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Phone Logs - Unidentified, 2000-2001; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Phone Logs - Unidentified 1 of 3, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Phone Logs - Unidentified 2 of 3, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Phone Logs - Unidentified 3 of 3, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Policy Committee, 1997 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Policy Statement on The Relationship Between Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation and Journey of Hope, 1998 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Policy Working Group Manual Draft, 2002 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Potential Associate Board Member, 2000 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Public Education (Program) Committee, 1997 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Quick Books (December 31), 1999 (Floppy-disk 11)
  - Quick Books, 2000 (Floppy-disk 12)
  - Quick Books - Accountant's Copy, 2001 (Floppy-disk 13)
  - Quick Books - Atts Changes to Import, Undated (Floppy-disk 14)
  - Quick Book Backup, 2000 (Floppy-disk 15)
  - Quick Book Backup, 2002 (Floppy-disk 16)
    Video
  - Quick Books Backup, Undated (Floppy-disk 17)
  - Quick Books Backup, Undated (Floppy-disk 18)
    Conference Materials
  - Quick Book Backup (November 4th and December 13th), 1999 (Floppy-disk 19)
  - Quicken Files (thru January 8, 1999), Undated (Floppy-disk 20)
  - Quicken Files Backup (1), Undated (Floppy-disk 21)
  - Quicken Files Backup (2) and Appendix Materials, Undated (Floppy-disk 22)
  - Quicken Files Backup (October), 2000 (Floppy-disk 23)
  - References-Susan McMahon, 1997; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Reference Materials for Strategic Planning, 1996-1997 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Resignation Letters, 1998 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Tax Forms - 941 and 941c, 2000-2002; Undated (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Transfer of Funds, 2000 (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Unemployment Insurance- Massachusetts, 1998; 2000 (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Unified Registration Statements for Charitable Organizations, Undated (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Vendor Expense Details, 2005 (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Virginia Employment Papers, 2005; Undated (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Virginia Nonprofit Registration, Undated (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - W-2 Wage and Tax Statements, 2004 (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Wells Fargo Loan Application, 1998; Undated (Box 4 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Resumes and Correspondence with Job Candidates, 2004; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Sandburg, Gonzalez, and Creedin, P.C. - Audit Agreement, 2002 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Strategic Planning Meeting, 1998; 2002; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Strategic Planning Meeting (September 13th), 2002 (Cassette 1)
  - Supporting Documents and Notes for 2003 Board Meeting, 1998; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Ta-1 Massachusetts Registration [Restricted], 1999-2000; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Tax Exemption Application, 1991-1993; 1996-1997; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Tax Forms [Restricted], 1999-2004 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Tax Forms - 941 Reports, 1999-2000; Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1994-2005, Undated; 2; 3.2 cubic ft.